A Guide to the James J. Kilpatrick Papers 1947-1967
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The James J. Kilpatrick Papers 1947-1967
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6626-c
35,680 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Library acquired these papers from James J. Kilpatrick, 14 Dec 1967.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of James J. Kilpatrick consist of speeches, 1951-1966; miscellaneous newspaper and magazine articles, 1947-1966; miscellaneous notes and manscripts on books; personal invitations, 1966; material dealing generally with the Doctrine of Interposition; material dealing with radio-television appearances, 1962-1967; and papers on Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr., 1925-1964.
Contents List
- Speeches 1951-1966
  - Rotary Club, Franklin, Virginia 1951 (Box 1)
  - Pi Delta Epsilon Journalism Sorority, Longwood College 1951 (Box 1)
  - Intercollegiate Press Association, Longwood College 1951 (Box 1)
  - Kiwanis Club, Richmond, Virginia, on the role of the press 1951 (Box 1)
  - Virginia Highway Users Association, Old Point Comfort 1952 (Box 1)
  - Academy of Medicine, Richmond 1953 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University School of Journalism 23 Feb 1953 (Box 1)
  - University of Missouri School of Journalism 30 Apr 1953 (Box 1)
  - Rotary Club, Columbia, Mo. 30 Apr 1953 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University, School of Journalism 26 Apr 1954 (Box 1)
  - Addresses on Dr. Douglas Southall Freeman 1954 (Box 1)
  - University of Richmond, on integration issue 1955 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous speech notes on race issue 1955 (Box 1)
  - South Carolina Press Association, Columbia, S.C. 1957 (Box 1)
  - On Spencer Roane, Hanover Courthouse 1957 (Box 1)
  - Sharon, Conn., on the race issue 1957 (Box 1)
  - The Virginian's Club, New York City 1957 (Box 1)
  - United Daughters of the Confederacy, Richmond 1958 (Box 1)
  - Inaugural Address for J. Lindsay Almond 1958 (Box 1)
  - Villanova Law School, Villanova College 1958 (Box 1)
  - Rotary Club, Richmond, on integration issue 1958 (Box 1)
  - Metuchen High School, Metuchen, N.J. on the Constitution 1958 (Box 1)
  - Morristown, N.J., on integration issue 1958 (Box 1)
  - Introduction of Gov. Marvin Griffin, Richmond 1959 (Box 2)
  - The City Club, Cleveland, Ohio, on integration issue 1959 (Box 2)
  - Farmville High School, commencement address 1959 (Box 2)
  - Phoenix, Arizona, on the Constitution 1959 (Box 2)
  - Dartmouth College, on the Consitution 1959 (Box 2)
  - Judicial Conference of Virginia, "The Literary Lawyer" 1959 (Box 2)
  - Original manuscript of doggerel "ode" marking the fifth anniversary of National Review magazine, Plaza Hotel, New York City 1960 (Box 2)
  - Testimonial dinner for William Workman, Columbia, S.C. 1960 (Box 2)
  - Camden High School, Camden, S.C. on the Constitution 1960 (Box 2)
  - Blue Ridge Writers' Colony, Hendersonville, N.C., on style in writing 1961 (Box 2)
  - Draft of address prepared for Gen. Edward Walker (but never delivered by him) 1961 (Box 3)
  - Virginia Teachers Association, on integration issue 1961 (Box 3)
  - Hampden-Sydney College, on integration issue 1962 (Box 3)
  - Pharmaceutical Manfacturer's Association, New York City 1962 (Box 3)
  - Longwood College, on Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr. 1963 (Box 3)
  - Texas Federation of Women's Clubs, Dallas 1963 (Box 3)
  - Virginia Commonwealth Attorneys' Association, on the trial of John Thomas Scopes 1963 (Box 3)
  - Virginia Bankers Association, Virginia Beach 1963 (Box 3)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution, Montpelier, Va., on the role of James Madison in the Virginia ratifying convention of 1788 1963 (Box 3)
  - University of Nevada, Reno, on civil rights 1963 (Box 3)
  - The Women's Club, Richmond 1963 (Box 3)
  - Public Affairs Club, Dallas, Texas, "A Time for Losing Tempers" 1963 (Box 3)
  - Hampden-Sydney College, on civil rights 1963 (Box 3)
  - John Randolph Society, University of Va., Charlottesville 1963 (Box 3)
  - Gladwyne Forum, Narberth, Pa., on the Constitution 1963 (Box 3)
  - Debate with James Farmer, director of the Congress of Racial Equality, Bryn Mawr-Haverford Colleges, Haverford, Pa. 1964 (Box 3)
  - Debate with Roy Wilkins, director of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, University of Minnesota, Minn. 1964 (Box 3)
  - Virginia Bankers Association, Natural Bridge 1964 (Box 3)
  - Pennsylvania State University, Harrisburg 1964 (Box 3)
  - South Carolina Chamber of Commerce, Columbia, S.C. 1964 (Box 3)
  - Washington and Lee University, Lexington, Va. 1964 (Box 3)
  - Debate with Ralph McGill, publisher of the Atlantic Constitution, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tenn. 1964 (Box 4)
  - St. John's Dinner Club, Jacksonville, Fla., "The Case for Conservatism" 1964 (Box 4)
  - The Richmond Bar Association, Richmond, Va. 1964 (Box 4)
  - Macon Academy, Tuskegee, Alabama, commencement address 1964 (Box 4)
  - Gallaudet College, Washington, D.C. on civil rights 1964 (Box 4)
  - Home Demonstration Clubs of Virginia, Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Blacksburg, on cybernetics 1964 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Judicial Conference, Roanoke, on "Free Press, Fair Trial" 1965 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Chamber of Commerce, annual dinner for Virginians in Congress, Washington, D.C., on "What Virginia Means to Me" 1965 (Box 4)
  - Wake Forest College, N.C., "The New Federalism" 1965 (Box 4)
  - West Point High School, West Point, Va., commencement address 1965 (Box 4)
  - Young Republican Club, Mary Washington College, Fredericksburg 1965 (Box 4)
  - Virginia Bankers Association, Staunton, on cybernetics 1965 (Box 4)
  - Southern States Probation and Parole Conference, Richmond 1965 (Box 4)
  - Dartmouth College, on civil rights 1965 (Box 4)
  - Prince Edward Academy, Farmville, Va., commencement address 1965 (Box 4)
  - Woman's Club, Newport News, Va. 1965 (Box 4)
  - Sons of the American Revolution, Philadelphia, Pa., "The Great Society" 1965 (Box 4)
  - Debate with the Rev. William Sloane Coffin, Chaplain, Yale University, New Haven, Conn., on civil rights 1965 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous local speeches 1965 (Box 4)
  - Debate with Roy Wilkins, director of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Blacksburg, Va., on civil rights 1966 (Box 4)
  - Law School, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, "Free Press, Fair Trial" 1966 (Box 4)
  - Lectures to Peace Corps Training School, Puerto Rico 1966 (Box 4)
  - Right-to-Work Conference, Philadelphia 1966 (Box 4)
  - Prince Edward Academy, Farmville, Va., on dedication of the James Jackson Kilpatrick Library 1966 (Box 4)
  - Albright College, Reading, Pa., on conservatism 1966 (Box 4)
  - The University of Alabama, Tuscaloosa, on the right to dissent 1966 (Box 4)
  - South Carolina Chamber of Commerce, Columbia, S.C., "Survival of the States" 1966 (Box 4)
  - Averett College, Danville, Va., "The State of the Union" 1966 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Articles: Newspapers and Magazines 1947-1966
  - Richmond Afternoon columns, Richmond News Leader1947 (Box 5)
  - Article, "Virginia Keeps Its Public Utilities Running," Public Utilities Fortnightly22 Dec 1949 (Box 5)
  - Article, "The Man Who Never Laughed," for Cavalcade Magazine n.d. (Box 5)
  - Article, with Charles Henry Hamilton, "The Rescue Squads Roll On," Reader's Digestn.d. (Box 5)
  - Article, "Conflict in Little Rock," National Review magazine n.d. (Box 5)
  - Article, "But it Won't Stay Buried," on the Byrd Organization, National Review8 Mar 1958 (Box 5)
  - Article, "The Anatomy of Liberalism," National Review 10 Oct 1959 (Box 5)
  - Article, "Diary for December 23," a Christmas story, first published in the News Leader1958 (Box 5)
  - Article, "Lyndon Johnson, Counterfeit Confederate," Human Events1960 (Box 5)
  - Essay, "Conservatism and the South," prepared for the Public Affiars Conference Center, University of Chicago 1961 (Box 5)
  - Review of Federal Censorship, by James C.N. Paul and Murray L. Schwartz, University of Pennsylvania Law Review1961 (Box 5)
  - Articles and Reviews, National Review1961 (Box 5)
  - Article, "When Virginia Joined the Union," Commonwealth Magazine Nov 1963 (Box 6)
  - Article, "The Hell He Is Equal," prepared for the Saturday Evening Post, but never published 1963 (Box 6)
  - Essay, "View From A Southern Exposure," on the Centennial Observance of the Emancipation Proclamation; Essay, "Reflections of a Sunday, 1963," prepared for the Public Affairs Conference Center, University of Chicago, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Articles, National Review1963 (Box 6)
  - Article, "The Ike Plan Cometh," National Review1964 (Box 6)
  - Articles, National Review1964 (Box 6)
  - Article, "A Southern Conservative View," Saturday Review25 Apr 1964 (Box 6)
  - Article, The RotarianDec 1965 (Box 6)
  - Article, "To Live in Dixie," Harper's1965 (Box 6)
  - Article on Negro voting rights, National Review20 Apr 1965 (Box 6)
  - Article, "Our Man at the Golliwog Lounge," on a meeting in Chicago of the Philadelphia Society, National Review1966 (Box 6)
  - Article, "Conservatism in our Time," Saturday Review8 Oct 1966 (Box 6)
  - Contribution to a symposium on editorial pages, the Bulletin, American Soceity of Newspaper Editors 1966 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous Notes and Manscripts on Books; Personal Invitations; Material Dealing Generally with the Doctrine of Interposition; Material dealing with Radio-Television Appearances 1962-1967 (Box 7-9)
- Senator Harry F. Byrd, Sr. 1925-1964
  - Leaflet, The Byrd-Anderson Controversy; Leaflet, "Reply to William Moseley Brown, Republican Candidate for Governor, by Harry F. Byrd, Governor of Virginia" Oct 1929 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous statements by Byrd 1925-1937 (Box 10)
  - Miscelleneous statements by Byrd 1938, 1940-1946 (Box 10)
  - Material from Byrd's campaign against Martin L. Hutchinson 1946 (Box 10)
  - Byrd's split with the National Democratic Party 1948 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous statements by Byrd 1947-1950 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous statements by Byrd 1951-1954 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous statements by Byrd 1957-1959 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous statements by Byrd 1960-1961 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous statements by Byrd 1962-1963 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous statements by Byrd 1964 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, other material, Byrd's campaign against Francis Pickins Miller 1952 (Box 11)
  - Speeches, other pro-Byrd material, campaign of 1952 (Box 11)
  - Speeches, other pro-Miller material, campaign of 1952 (Box 11)
  - Letters to the News Leader Forum, Byrd-Miller Campaign 1952 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous biographical material (Box 11)
  - Manuscript and working notes, Kilpatrick's Longwood College essay 1963 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence between Kilpatrick and Byrd; photographs of Byrd and Kilpatrick, on top of Old Rag 1958-1963, June 1962 (Box 11)
  - Byrd's handwritten text of speech he delivered on Skyline Drive 9 Jun 1962 (Box 11)